Guide to the Frederic B. M. Hollyday Papers, 1943-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Frederic B. M. Hollyday papers 1943-1971
Duke University. University Archives
Hollyday, Federic B. M.
2.0 linear feet Extent: 2000 Items
Frederic Hollyday was a professor in the Dept. of History from 1956-1982. The collection includes meeting minutes, memoranda and relating to his research and administrative duties and ranges in date from 1943-1971.
UA.29.02.0141
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Frederic B. M. Hollyday Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1960-1977.
Biographical Note
Frederic Blackmar Mumford Hollyday was born in Easton Maryland in 1928. He received his B.A. from Washington and Lee University in 1948, and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Duke University in 1950 and 1955, respectively. He joined the faculty of the Duke History Department in 1956, and he specialized in 19th century German history. In 1968 and 1971, he served as Director of Undergraduate Studies in the History Department. Among his major publications include the books Bismarck's Rival: A Political Biography of General and Admiral Albrecht von Stosch (1960), Bismark: Great Lives Observed (1970), and the edited volume of E. Malcolm Carroll's The Western Powers and Soviet Russia, 1917-1922. He was promoted to Professor in 1971 and served in that capacity until his death in 1982.
Collection Overview
The collection includes personal, professional and official material, primarily correspondence and memoranda, concerning Holly's training and his subsequent career in Duke's History Dept. and his service on the Honors Committee of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. There is correspondence with Harold Lewis, E. M. Carroll and other historians which documents the way in which the department sought to bring along young scholars; other letters illustrate concerns the faculty had over matters such as segregation and race relations in the 1950s and 1960s. Some letters describe preparations for E. M. Carroll's Festschrift. There is a small amount of family correspondence and material relating to Hollyday's teaching and professional activities, such as National Archives conferences and the Southern Historical Association. Also included are the records of the Undergraduate Faculty Council Committee on Honors which Hollyday chaired in the late 1960s and probably received records from his predecessors. The collection ranges in date from 1943-1971.
Subject Headings
Hollyday, Frederic B. M.; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. Dept. of History; Duke University. Dept. of History -- Faculty; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council; Germany -- Study and teaching (Higher)
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Trinity College Historical Society Collection, [1492?]-1981
Duke University Archives
Frederic B. M. Hollyday Papers, 1818-1982
Rare Books, Manuscripts and Special Collections Library, Duke University
Frederic B. M. Hollyday [Miscellaneous Writings], Pamphlet Collection
Perkins/Bostock Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Jefferson Encyclopedia (Box 1)
  - Rutgers - Stearns Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Southgate Program (Box 1)
  - Mary Carroll - Clipping and Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Re: Purchase of Library Materials, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Thacker Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Summer Session, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Heniger Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Neal Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
  - The Story of Two Wars, 1950 (Box 1)
  - European Studies Program, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Washington and Lee/Shaw - 1966 Ceremony (Box 1)
  - Editorship - Central European Affairs, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Alabama Offer, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Morier Affair Article and Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Army Reserve Applications, Report Cards, 1949-1977 (Box 1)
  - Diaz Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Steinmetz Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Nipperdey Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1969, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Department Committees, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Central European History Conference Group, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Candidate Selection Procedure, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Dorian Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Krause Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Acting Director - Undergraduate Studies, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Courses, 1973 (Box 2)
  - History Department Meetings, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Fulbright Information, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Microform Review, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Program in History, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Stark - Prentice Hall Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Department Bylaws (Box 2)
  - Core Collection for College Libraries (Box 2)
  - Summer Session, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Assistantship Program (Box 2)
  - New Curriculum, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Leyburn Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2)
  - J. Swell Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - National Archives Materials (Box 2)
  - Pitcher Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Library Research Sources, Southern Historical Association, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Pass/Fail Memo, undated (Box 2)
  - Boschan Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
  - University of Wisconsin Seminar, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Duke Salaries, General Info, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Deans and Freshman Faculty Fellows (Box 2)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Faculty Council (Box 2)
  - United Fund Campaign, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Southern Historical Association - Memos and Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Woodrow Wilson National Fellowships, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Department Committees, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Procedures, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Kirk Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Student Job, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Introductory Course Report (Box 2)
  - Southern Historical Association Conference, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Duke Bylaws (Box 2)
  - Conference Group - Central Europe (Box 2)
  - Department Report - Southern Association (Box 2)
  - Archival Conference (Box 2)
  - High School Teachers, 1964 (Box 2)
  - History Honors Program (Box 2)
  - Forms to Send to Departments Having Graduation with Distinction Programs (Box 3)
  - Approved Graduation with Distinction Programs (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Departments Re: Distinction Programs (Box 3)
  - Minutes, Rulings on Special Cases (Box 3)
  - Graduation Programs, 1957-1965 (Box 3)
  - Honors Committee - Evaluation Responses (Box 3)
  - Honors Programs - Original Copy, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Honors, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Candidates for Graduation with Distinction, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Honors Papers, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Honors at Duke, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Duke Programs in Graduation with Distinction, 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Honors Programs and Brochures, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Honors Committee Report, 1965-1969 (Box 4)
  - Honors Materials (Box 4)
  - Graduation with Distinction Candidate Memos, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Graduation with Distinction Candidates, 1968-1969 (Box 4)